arthritis is no joke from the pain and
stiffness in the joints across the body
to the inflammation that never ceases
being able to manage it and even improve
the majority if not all of the symptoms
with one supplement would be pretty
impressive and aren't we just in luck
because such a supplement does exist so
let's discuss the science because
there's been at least 30 studies that
have looked into this antiarthritis
effect so so we'll go over it briefly
the mechanisms by which it works and
then go into the clinical data detailing
all the ways that it improves arthritis
including some details that you've
probably never heard before even if
you've watched other content
on curcumin curcumin is a molecule found
inside the turmeric spice and that's
been extensively researched on its
benefits some that I've covered in the
past but there's been a ton of work in
relation to rheumatoid and
osteoarthritis curcumin Works through a
number of mechanisms and I'd like to get
into some of the detail in some of these
mechanisms in other content because they
deserve their own deep Dives but for now
know that curcumin molecule reduces the
expression or the production of key
inflammation molecules like inter lucans
interferons tumor necrosis Factor
essentially cumin stops these molecules
from being produced by if we take short
stroll through your cells binding a
protein complex called inhibitor of
Kappa beta kyes complex will abbreviate
it as ik K curcumin is able to stop
specific proteins that Branch off this
complex from binding the genes that
produce the inflammatory molecules that
we just went over so the inter lucans
interferons and so on normally if these
proteins were to peel off and bind these
genes these genes would be red and more
of these inflammatory molecules would be
produced leading to a stronger immune
response and more pain signals obviously
not what we want in arthritis cumin
attempts to stop that from happening but
beyond the direct anti-inflammatory
effects it can also inhibit the
overactivity of synovial cells in the
joints these cells are responsible for
the production of synovial fluid a
necessary component to a healthy joint
however if they are overactive they can
also contribute to inflammation and pain
cumin quiets them from an overactive
state to a normally active State there's
also some wildly cool mechanisms
curcumin has on bone in osteoarthritis
especially but I'll leave that for
dedicated content tell me if you're
interested because there's so much more
depth here that I'm not mentioning let's
move on to what you really care about if
well if you have arthritis what does
curcumin do to your function your well
being your joint pain well let's get
into that first let me introduce the
analysis that we'll be leaning on in
this analysis the researchers pulled 30
randomized control trials together into
a wonderful metaanalysis I say it's
wonderful because I've seen few meta
analyses that have been performed this
well I usually do some level of
secondary inspection by opening some of
the individual included studies and make
sure that they did certain things
correctly and the researchers did
everything really well first of all they
Incorporated many databases to find all
the studies that they could they even
included databases that house studies
that show no effect in unpublished data
this is important because without this
it biases the entire analysis to find an
effect if you don't include the data
that indicates no effect they also used
a massive list of keywords to find all
the studies that they could and they
even use studies in Chinese as well
which increases the pool of available
studies this was all very very well done
okay enough babbling about the
methodology let's discuss the results
first off they looked at some
inflammation metrics like C-reactive
protein or CRP and C-reactive protein is
an overall inflammation metric released
by your liver it rises in response to
body inflammation if you have higher CRP
levels your bodily inflammation is
generally heightened here's that data
I'm going to walk you through how to
read this but if you're already familiar
or you just just don't care then skip to
this timestamp on the left side are the
study names and then all the numbers in
the middle are the CRP values extracted
from each study from the curcumin
condition in each study called the
experimental and from the non- curcumin
consuming group called The control now I
won't go over the mean the standard
deviation and all that jazz I have a
course that explains all that if you're
interested in learning how to analyze
studies for yourself however to the
right of the numbers we see green boxes
and a black diamond those are the
graphical representation of the numbers
much easier to read see the line above
zero that's the mark for no detected
effect of cumin if the individual green
boxes which represent the study results
move to the left it indicates an effect
of curcumin and if they move to the
right it means there's a likely worse
effect with cumin finally you'll note
the risk of bias on the very right this
is a another analysis that researchers
are often required to do it's a
standardized system where they report
the risk of bias across a number of
measurements of potential bias generally
the more green that you see the lower
the potential bias however you'll rarely
ever see all green because in analyses
of these sizes you'll inevitably include
some studies that have a higher risk of
bias and some risk is unavoidable
there's more to say on this topic but
we've got some results to get to and I'd
like to acknowledge one more thing thing
that the researchers did really well
again skip to this Tim stamp if you
really don't care I can't help myself I
just like highlighting great work
especially since I'm often so critical
so notice that this Amal study shows up
twice and so does the Jacob study they
show up twice because they had two
separate intervention groups meaning two
different groups were given curcumin
instead of choosing one group and
ignoring the other researchers are
allowed to add both groups to the
analysis as long as they follow certain
rules one the groups have to be distinct
so you can't say the same group of
participants in that study were exposed
to two different concentrations of
curcumin just at different times those
are dependent groups because it's the
same group of people just at two
different times however in this case it
has two completely different groups of
people given different amounts of cumin
the second thing is that the researchers
of the analysis have to do is split the
comparison group what does that mean
there's only one control group yet two
intervention so cumin groups as a result
you can't compare both intervention
groups against the same control group
because it artificially inflates the
results there's some complexity that I
won't go over for now so either the
researchers can choose to only include
one intervention group from the study
although there are two or they can split
the control group which means that they
assign half the control group to be
compared against one cumin group and the
other half to be compared against the
other cumin group this effectively
rebalances the results I can't tell you
how many analyses fail to do that it's
not necessarily a deal breaker but it
does reduce the confidence in the
results that they're actually accurate
if they're on the edge between
statistically significant or not anyway
I double checked a few these comparisons
by opening the individual studies and
was very pleasantly surprised these
researchers nailed it serious kudos to
them I realize you might be wondering
who in the world cares dude and from my
perspective understanding this stuff is
part of a complete education I don't
believe just telling people the answer
but rather showing them the train of
thought and it's important for people to
see the background work that goes into
this referencing
abstracts runs wul short of the
necessary work anyway I promise I'll
stop at the statistics at least for the
most part let's rejoin the 99% that
skipped to the timestamp So based on
these data on CRP levels the Black
Diamond which corresponds to the average
value across all the studies combined
cument does reduce the inflammatory
marker CRP this is confirmed
statistically as well there's another
important thing to say about this along
with all the other measures but I'll
address that at the end let's move on
another measure is rheumatoid factor or
RF this is an antibody that binds to our
own tissues and identifies it as other
or not of self which promotes a strong
inflammatory response by the immune
system now RF especially binds what's
known as the FC region of an IGG
antibody the dominant type of antibody
in your body is IGG and there's a
section that is called the FC region now
RF will bind to that FC region and
create a complex in doing so the immune
cells are drawn to that region leading
to an inflamatory Cascade as seen in
rheumatoid arthritis so what happens
when we consume curcumin well let's look
we can see the four studies or more
accurately the four arms of two Studies
by the Black di clearly to the left
indicating a benefit of cumin confirmed
statistically now I'd also add that
these results are remarkably consistent
with zero heterogen for those in the no
okay so across two inflammation and
arthritis markers cumin provides a
benefit but we're not just interested in
inflammation we want to understand if
there are functional improvements can
people move more easily experience fewer
symptoms and so on so let's look at that
for that we'll rely on the
das28 test that stands for the disease
activity score in 28 joints the higher
the value of this score the greater
one's pain so swollen joints so the
lower the score the better looking at
those data we again see cumin provides
benefit again confirmed statistically
now I do wish they did uh do further
analysis by picking out the least risk
of bias studies and seeing if that would
change the results because you might
notice that the three studies or
conditions that are the lowest risk of
buys show no effect it would be nice at
least to tease that out however looking
at some other measures like the wmax
score which is another test of
functional ability the higher quality
studies confirm curcumin's effect okay
we're not done yet because there's a few
important things that you should know
before we close this out before we get
to those there's also additional
information comparing cumin to other
joint support molecules like glucosamine
crotin and more I'll be covering that
along with the optimal dosing of
curcumin and more in the extended
version of this video that you're
watching which if you've been here for a
while you know it's all included in the
physionic Insiders along with access to
all my work and much much more you can
join via the link in the description I
hope to see you there now what's so
important well for one all the
comparisons that we've looked at are
against a control group remember non
cumin but that doesn't mean it's a pure
comparison that could be a drug it could
be another supplement and so on I mean
that if we want to get a real sense of
curcumin's effects we need to look at
curcumin versus something like a placebo
a true non- curcumin comparison not
another active ingredient fortunately
the researchers split the controls apart
and isolated the studies only comparing
against Placebo and here are the results
the top comparison is against Placebo
only and we're looking at that wac
measure that I mentioned earlier a
measure of pain overall it seems
curcumin again confirms in a more pure
comparison that it is effective against
arthritis pain however if you ease your
eyes down a bit they also compare
against conventional pain medication
called Nets to be be fair there's only
one study but it's a very low risk of
biased study and there's no advantage of
cumin in that comparison however is that
a bad thing likely not it should be
interpreted that curcumin is not more
effective but is as effective as
conventional pain relief medication so
that's not bad at all another important
Point here to look at is the effect
sizes as in sure there's an effect but
how how big is the effect is it worth my
while the answer is a bit surprising for
example that Das 28 test that we looked
at earlier show a 1.06 Point reduction
compared to all controls but what is the
scale of the
das28 is it a twoo scale or is it a 50o
scale it turns out it's a 10-point scale
so it's about a 10% improvement with
cumin not bad but not earth sh battery
that said what happens when we look at
the pure comparison there the effect is
again relatively mild although it does
seem to improve across multiple
different types of problems like
swelling pain stiffness and so on
however on metrix of inflammation cumin
has some pretty fantastic effects for
example the rheumatoid factor is reduced
by around 50 points which would
completely shift a person from one whole
category of disease to another from
let's say severe to moderate arthritis
as one example that's really amazing so
where does that leave everything
curcumin a yes or a no for
arthritis well it seems clear that
curcumin supplementation mildly improves
rheumatoid and osteoarthritis symptoms
the effect size on the clinical measures
isn't huge but it is widespread on the
other hand some of the inflammation
measures do show pretty significant
improvements I'd also add that curcumin
was shown with limited evidence to
improve arthritis symptoms on par with
nonsteroid anti-inflammatory drugs which
is also quite impressive now if you're
suffering from arthritis symptoms it's
probably worthwhile to consider cumin
and something else to consider is this
next video that I have linked for you
thanks for tuning in and all the best to
you bye
[Music]
oh